<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Andrew Hammond]]></title>
  <link href="http://andrhamm.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://andrhamm.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-04T15:23:21-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://andrhamm.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Hammond]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Update Java to Fix ElasticSearch "Unsupported major.minor Version 51.0"]]></title>
    <link href="http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/08/04/update-java-to-fix-elasticsearch-unsupported-major-dot-minor-version-51-dot-0/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-04T15:11:54-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/08/04/update-java-to-fix-elasticsearch-unsupported-major-dot-minor-version-51-dot-0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I went to install ElasticSearch with Homebrew on Mac OS X, I got the following error message when trying to start up ElasticSearch: <code>"Unsupported major.minor version 51.0"</code>. I found the experience kind of sucky, with a lot of misleading or generally unhelpful posts out there when Googling. So naturally I figured I&rsquo;d add to the confusion. Here is how I solved the problem on my machine. <!-- more --></p>

<p>Find out which version of Java you are using:</p>

<pre><code>java -version
</code></pre>

<p>This is probably 1.6 if you are on Mac OS X. That was my case, and I needed 1.7 for ElasticSearch.</p>

<p>See where your Java lives:</p>

<pre><code>which java
</code></pre>

<p>This is probably <code>/usr/bin/java</code> if you haven&rsquo;t monkied with your native install.</p>

<p>Download <a href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/downloads/jdk7-downloads-1880260.html">JDK 1.7</a></p>

<pre><code>http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/downloads/jdk7-downloads-1880260.html
</code></pre>

<p>I restarted at this point but my symlink (<code>which java</code>) didn&rsquo;t update. It seems like kind of a shitty way to get what you want, but setting your <code>JAVA_HOME</code> environment variable will now point your scripts to the right version:</p>

<pre><code>export JAVA_HOME="`/usr/libexec/java_home -v '1.7*'`"
</code></pre>

<p>This sort of stuff seems to come up anytime you mention JDK or JVM being a dependency of anything. Sweet dice&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Downsizing Sucks]]></title>
    <link href="http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/07/24/downsizing-sucks/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-24T22:12:43-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/07/24/downsizing-sucks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s 10pm and, after debating the issue for quite a while now, I decided to take the first step in downsizing one of my hobbies. Downsizing a hobby really sucks, but sometimes it&rsquo;s for the best. In this case, the hobby is homebrewing. I&rsquo;ve been homebrewing for about 3 years, and the whole time has been on an upward trend as far as my obsession for it goes, but lately it has really taken a back seat. We recently bought our first house and in the move, and settling in, and enjoying all the new space and freedom (like beeing able to build a chicken coop), my half-baked 20 Gallon Electric Brewery project was put on hold. Well, I just posted my three, never been used, 20 gallon brew kettles for sale online&hellip;</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="http://imgur.com/a/S4t12/embed"></iframe>


<p><em>read on for my reasoning behind this terrible downsizing</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>After spending a year building an <a href="http://theelectricbrewery.com">Electric Brewery</a> control panel on my own, and just barely having seen it come to life before moving, I&rsquo;m already looking to downsize the system. Here are some of my reasons, which I&rsquo;m writing down partly because I&rsquo;m still trying to convince myself it is the right choice.</p>

<p>1) Our house is far from my workplace now. So what, right? Well one of my favorite parts about brewing was having friends and coworkers over and having a great brew day. One of the trade-offs of moving this far away for our dream house was that those friends likely won&rsquo;t be making the trip for brew day anymore. I don&rsquo;t blame them. It&rsquo;s over an hour by train and nearly as long in weekend traffic when driving.</p>

<p>2) Since I take that hour+ long train ride to work now, I won&rsquo;t be off-loading kegs of homebrew for the office keggerator any time soon. That leaves me with 3 kegs of beer after every brew day. What am I supposed to do with all that?</p>

<p>3) Trying to get through 15 gallons of beer after each brew session would require me to only brew once in a blue moon. My favorite part of brewing is the experimentation and exploration involved &ndash; <del>trying</del> creating new recipes. But sometimes, experiments fail. In fact many of my homebrew experiments have failed. Hell, I think I have 30 gallons of (probably) ruined/gross/meh homebrew in various states around my house (in the keggerator, in the breezeway sitting in carboys since the move, in kegs in the closet, in old bottles somewhere in the moving boxes) and I know I&rsquo;ve dumped that much down the drain early on. With the 20 gallon system, my minimum brew size would have been around 10 gallons, but more likely 15 gallons would be the average batch size. That is a lot of beer to mess up.. there is more on the line with the large system. I got cocky and made my system too big for my level of experience (although I planned to grow into it).</p>

<p>4) By selling <em>just one</em> of my kettles, I&rsquo;ll be able to get three new ones of a more reasonable size. Good news is, stainless steel doesn&rsquo;t really lose value in the homebrew world. I really like the MegaPot 1.2s, so I&rsquo;m planning on going with those again, but in the 8 gallon size. The remaining two pots I&rsquo;ll still sell, and hopefully with a piece of that I can afford a decent fermenter. Like a small conical or a couple of the new stainless steel &ldquo;bucket&rdquo; style fermenters which have a slight cone at the bottom. I really think not fermenting in stainless is the last major problem with my brewing (causing minor off flavors).</p>

<p>So there you have it. I&rsquo;ll be downsizing to an 8 gallon electric HERMs brewery. Yes, of course I&rsquo;ll still use my amazing control panel. Seriously, it took over a year to build.</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="http://imgur.com/a/8a12t/embed"></iframe>


<p>Cheers!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stay-cation Projects Update]]></title>
    <link href="http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/07/13/stay-cation-projects-update/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-13T09:00:15-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/07/13/stay-cation-projects-update</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I decided to take a couple days off of work to catch up on some of my projects at home. Taking Thursday and Friday off gave me a nice 4 day vacation, or &ldquo;stay-cation&rdquo;, as they say, since I stayed home for it. It&rsquo;s Sunday morning and I&rsquo;ve already gotten a lot done and still have a whole day to go.</p>

<p>In just three days I&rsquo;ve organized our garage (it was a disaster), built a solid workbench, got my hydroponics experiment working, started a new colony of Black Soldier Flies, and built a really nice door for the chicken coop. Keep reading for quick summary of each of these projects along with pictures.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Chicken Coop Door</h3>

<p>Up until now, the coop run (the open area outside the &ldquo;cabin&rdquo;) has been fully enclosed with hardware cloth, including the spot where a door should be, making it impossible for me to get in there without removing staples and getting cut by the sharp edges of the mesh. So after a couple weeks of planning, I acquired the tools I needed to make a good door.</p>

<p>Having just moved to this, our first house, from a series of apartments, my tool collection was lacking some woodworking essentials. Having a lot of difficulty with squaring up joints in previous projects, this time I picked up a variety of different clamps to get the job done right. My two new 48&#8221; pipe clamps might be my new favorite tools. These things are super handy and strong.</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="http://imgur.com/a/hV0cZ/embed"></iframe>


<p>As you can see in the photos, I squared everything up and clamped it all down tight. I decided it would be too difficult to try to toe screw the 1&#8221;x4&#8221; pine boards at the corners, so I ended up relying on small pieces of 1&#8221;x4&#8221; cut with 45° ends for a good connection. I screwed those to the frame and it turned out to be really sturdy and, best of all, square.</p>

<p>After that, the frame was ready for a layer of hardware cloth, which was stapled down liberally for a tight and flat bond. I added more of the diagonal pieces of 1&#8221;x4&#8221; on top of the hardware cloth, sandwiching it between the two layers of the frame. This gave the door a ton of rigidity and a classic barn style.</p>

<p>To attach the door to the coop I had to add a few new studs for support and to put the hinge on the correct plane so the door would be flush when closed. I used a heavy duty Stanely spring-loaded hinge, the same as the one on the back door of the coop&rsquo;s cabin. The hinge is spring-loaded so it will close (at an adjustable speed/force) if accidentally left open.</p>

<p>Overall, the door turned out way better than I expected. I outdid myself on this one. All that is left is adding a latch and a few coats of paint!</p>

<h3>Workbench</h3>

<p>My favorite aspect of home-ownership, after years of renting apartments, is having the space for doing all these projects. A solid, rugged workbench is a must for somebody who stays as busy as I do. Previously I had been doing all my projects (like building an Electric Brewery control panel) on an IKEA table covered with a layer of cardboard&hellip; not exactly ideal for banging on things and just generally making a mess of things. After a lengthy garage clean-out, there was a lot of space to fill, and a workbench fit the bill.</p>

<p>I expected to spend a lot of time planning, but I came across a <a href="http://www.familyhandyman.com/workshop/workbench/how-to-build-a-workbench-super-simple-50-bench/view-all">great design with complete plans</a> almost immediately with some quick Googling. The plans turned out to be extremely well thought-out, as they produced close to zero waste. Luckily, I had all of the building materials I needed which were leftover from the coop build. I highly recommend the plans for this workbench if you&rsquo;re looking to build one yourself.</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="http://imgur.com/a/rnKYc/embed"></iframe>


<p>The materials and the cost breakdown:</p>

<p>16 x 2&#8221;x4&#8221;x8&#8217; stud (about $3 ea.) (<em>$50</em>)
1 x 4&#8217;x8&#8217; plywood board (<em>$15</em>)
1 x 4&#8217;x8&#8217; peg board (<em>$17</em>)
1 x 1lb of 3&#8221; deck screws (<em>$10</em>)
1 x 1/2lb of 1.5&#8221; deck screws (<em>$5</em>)
1 x Hanging shop light enclosure (<em>$30</em>)
2 x T8 shop light bulb (<em>$5</em>)
1 x Metal housing power strip (<em>$23</em>)
Misc peg-board accessories (<em>$20</em>)
<strong>Total Cost: $175</strong></p>

<h3>Hydroponics</h3>

<p>I finished a project that had been stalled after finding an item in my house while unpacking some moving boxes that would work perfectly as a media guard. Previous attempts at making a media guard that would keep the HydroCorn from getting sucked into the bell siphon had failed, but this new two-stage design seems to work well.</p>

<p>I wrapped some mesh-like fabric around the PVC media guard from the last attempt and secured it with rubber bands. The fabric is longer than the guard and that is on purpose; it kind of folds in toward the bell siphon, creating a barrier along the bottom (as opposed to just the sides). The new piece of the equation came in the form of a cheap pencil holder from IKEA. It already had holes in it and, best of all, had a bottom unlike the PVC. I cut a whole to fit the drain through and placed it between the seal of the growbed, making a water tight seal that would also hold the media guard in place. Part of the fault of the PVC filter alone was that it would be pulled up when the HydroCorn would float as the water rose. This design keeps it pressed firmly to the bottom of the bed.</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="http://imgur.com/a/1pdyj/embed"></iframe>


<p>I&rsquo;ll do more hydroponics updates in the future, as I&rsquo;m hoping to integrate a tank with many goldfish to make it a true small-scale <em>auqua</em>ponics ecosystem. My first attempt failed, resulting in the loss of 14 goldfish.</p>

<h3>Upcoming posts</h3>

<p>In the next post, I&rsquo;ll give a tour of my Black Soldier Fly harvesting strategy, which is more of an experiment right now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chickens Moved Into the Coop]]></title>
    <link href="http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/06/30/chickens-moved-into-the-coop/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-30T10:01:33-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/06/30/chickens-moved-into-the-coop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This weekend marked a big milestone for our homestead. I made enough progress on the coop build on Saturday that I was able to move the chickens from their 4&#8217; x 4&#8217; brooder (inside a spare room of our house) to the cabin part of the coop before the sun set. I was able to keep an eye on them all of Sunday and make a few adjustments as needed. Check out the album.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I added a couple simple supports to mount the roost to. There are two roosts (and the smaller one from their old brooder) made from a branch of the tree I had to cut down while building the roof of the coop. I think it is better to use a natural roost instead of the other option of making them out of 2&#8217; x 4&#8217; lumber.</p>

<p>I also set up a new hanging feeder since they outgrew their chick feeder weeks ago. This one hangs from the ceiling to just a few inches off the floor of the cabin and helps prevent the feeder from being filled up with bedding and waste.</p>

<p>I finished enclosing the entire run with hardware cloth (better than chicken wire), but I didn&rsquo;t tackle making the main door so I just temporarily stapled hardware cloth right over the opening. Unfortunately this means I can&rsquo;t get in to the run until I&rsquo;m ready to install the door.</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="http://imgur.com/a/mPOcm/embed"></iframe>


<p>There is definitely still a lot to do. Primarily the front door, but also the nest box needs to be finished and the area around the coop will need some landscaping. I&rsquo;m contemplating which kinds of shrubs and mulch to use. The area gets mostly shade during the day. I also plan to build a removable sandbox for the girls to take their dust baths in.</p>

<p>Stay tuned for more updates!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chicken Coop Build Progress]]></title>
    <link href="http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/06/23/chicken-coop-build-progress/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-23T10:23:31-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/06/23/chicken-coop-build-progress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent another 25 hours or so on my chicken coop this weekend. I&rsquo;ll roll all this into a more detailed post at some point, but for now check out this album.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This weekend was mostly spent on the cabin part of the coop (as opposed to the larger, open &ldquo;run&rdquo;). This is where the chickens will roost at night. I decided to line the floor of the coop with linoleum flooring, to protect the wood from absorbing any of the nasty smells/fluids from the chicken waste. It should also make it much easier to clean out periodically.</p>

<p>The front of the coop has a window to let in some natural sunlight and allow for needed ventilation in the summer. I covered the window with hardware cloth (strong chicken wire) from the inside, but will add a sheet of clear plexy-glass before the fall/winter season for weather proofing.</p>

<p>The entire back side of the coop is a swinging door with a really beefy hinge (spring-loaded to prevent the door from remaining open) and latch. This door is essential for cleaning out the cabin and is the only way a person can get into the coop.</p>

<p>The siding is all tongue &amp; groove boards which makes for a very time-consuming build. I&rsquo;m not complaining though, my father-in-law Chuck had it left over from his house build and gave it to me for free! Similar boards at Lowe&rsquo;s run about $10 each. Each! I would have just left it at plywood if that was my only option, but I had so many of these boards left over that I figured this would be well worth the extra effort. I love how the siding looks, with its nice horizontal grooves, it really adds to the desired &ldquo;barn&rdquo; look. Of course the &ldquo;barn door red&rdquo; paint with white trim really paid off too!</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="http://imgur.com/a/jtQfY/embed"></iframe>


<p>Stay tuned for more updates on the coop.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exclude Properties From JBuilder Partials]]></title>
    <link href="http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/06/18/exclude-properties-from-jbuilder-partials/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-18T15:04:23-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/06/18/exclude-properties-from-jbuilder-partials</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found the lack of documentation for JBuilder partials to be very frustrating. Ideally I could write one partial for each of my ActiveRecord models and re-use them in all my JBuilder views. The problem comes when you have a model like User, for example, which has one or more Photos. When I request the <code>show</code> action for my User controller, I want the User partial to be rendered with it&rsquo;s Photo as a child (using the Photo partial). On the other hand, when I request the <code>show</code> action for my Photo, I want the Photo partial to be rendered with it&rsquo;s User as a child (using the User partial). This can lead to an infinite loop which, at first glance, can only be solved by making many individual partials for the same model, like <code>photo_without_user</code> and <code>photo_with_user</code>.<!-- more --></p>

<p>Going a little deeper, you&rsquo;ll find that the <code>partial!</code> method will pass any data you give it along to the view (the unrecognized hash keys will be available to the view as local variables of the same name). In the following example, I simply pass a custom variable, <code>exclude</code>, into the call to <code>partial!</code> and use it as a condition in the photo partial view. Obviously this will grow cumbersome if you are nesting partials more than a couple layers deep, but for my use, it works quite well.</p>

<pre><code># In `users/_user.json.jbuilder`:
json.(user, :id, :name)
json.photo do
  json.partial! 'photos/photo', photo: user.photo, exclude: [:user]
end
</code></pre>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<pre><code># In `photos/_photo.json.jbuilder`:
json.(photo, :url, :caption)
unless exclude.include?(:user)
  json.user do
    json.partial! 'users/user', user: photo.user
  end
end
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
