<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Homebrewing | Andrew Hammond]]></title>
  <link href="http://andrhamm.com/blog/categories/homebrewing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://andrhamm.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-13T14:17:06-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://andrhamm.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Hammond]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Run of the Basement Brewery]]></title>
    <link href="http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/10/13/first-run-of-the-basement-brewery/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-13T10:30:59-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/10/13/first-run-of-the-basement-brewery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Brew: 12 gallons of <a href="www.theelectricbrewery.com/brew-day-step-by-step">Kal&rsquo;s Blonde Ale</a>
Start Time: Sunday, 4pm
End Time: Sunday 10pm
Problems encountered: many</p>

<!-- more -->




<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="//imgur.com/a/bitoe/embed"></iframe>


<p>As expected, the maiden voyage of my &ldquo;The Electric Brewery&rdquo; system pointed out several flaws in the current setup, not to mention, reminds me that no matter how many times I read a set of instructions, I&rsquo;m going to mess some things up.</p>

<p>Before the brew day really even officially began, I made a big mistake&hellip; As I stepped away for lunch, I turned off the HLT recirculation pump but forgot to turn off the heating element. This resulted in the water touching the PID temp probe to cool way down past the setpoint. As you can imagine, the PID thought it needed to catch up, so the element turned on and stayed on. The full 20 gallons in the HLT was nearly boiling by the time I made my way back to the brewery. It takes a really long time for 20G of 200ºF water too cool down to 148ºF&hellip;</p>

<p>When the HLT cooled down, we started the mash and discovered that the HLT coil is so tight, that the water inside the coil forms a column which makes it impossible for the wort inside the coil to hit the setpoint. Compounding the effect was the recirc output at the top of the HLT. It was spraying the returned water into the open air (pointed at the side of the inside of the pot). Even with the lid on, this seemed to be causing a fair amount of heat loss. I temporarily, kind of solved both problems by using a hose for the return (instead of the weldless bulkhead input) and pointing it directly at the coil. This quickly improved heat transfer to the wort inside the coil, allowing the mash temp to finally reach the setpoint after having been stuck well below it for around 30 mins.</p>

<p>ABRUPT ENDING! I&rsquo;ve had this post in progress (minimized and lonely) for exactly 1 month (started 10/13&hellip; it is now 11/13) and at this point I&rsquo;m on the verge of my second brew day, so I&rsquo;m giving up on this post, since you&rsquo;ll read more about the improvements I&rsquo;ve made in my next post.</p>

<p>Cheers!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Drying Homegrown Hops]]></title>
    <link href="http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/09/10/drying-homegrown-hops/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-10T09:55:14-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/09/10/drying-homegrown-hops</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend I was given 5 one quart freezer bags full of homegrown Nugget hops from my wife&rsquo;s grandma. This is just a quick post showing how I processed them for later use.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/ApktF29.jpg" alt="Homegrown hops" /></p>

<p>(Read on)</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The hops came to me within a day or two of being picked, so they were very fresh and still had a lot of moisture content. This, of course, needs to be removed before storage and use. I did some quick research and learned that they need to be dried in temperatures no greater than 100ºF. This is because some of the volatile hop oils and compounds (which are important for flavor and) will start to vaporize at higher temps.</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="//imgur.com/a/EvYkJ/embed"></iframe>


<p>I had previously ordered a variation of the super popular STC-1000 digital thermostat when it showed up on sale on <a href="http://homebrewfinds.com">HomeBrewFinds</a>. This thermostat can be found online for as low as $6 when ordered from Chinese eBay stores. I didn&rsquo;t want to wait 3 months for that, so when the $13.50 listing showed up on Amazon Prime with fast shipping, I jumped on it. I think that is a great deal when compared to the $60+ digital controls out there. So anyway, I didn&rsquo;t know what I&rsquo;d be using it for at the time, but when these hops showed up, I knew I&rsquo;d use it to whip up a simple hop dehydrator.</p>

<p>With parts I had laying around, I was able to wire up a simple temp controlled relay. All it took was the STC-1000, some wire, a used extension cord with the end cut off, and a spare wall power outlet. The STC came with a &ldquo;waterproof&rdquo; thermocouple (temp probe).</p>

<p>With the unit assembled, I plugged in the cheap food dehydrator (for the second time in the long time we&rsquo;ve owned it) to act as the kiln. Since the dehydrator only had 1 heat setting (on) and was far too hot for my purposes, I programmed for a conservative 90ºF. This is because I was anticipating hotspots, since I was really cramming the hops in there and limiting the air/heat circulation. All 5 layers of the dehydrator were fully loaded. I probably should have just done the drying in two batches, but in the end it worked out.</p>

<p>After running all night long, the hops were nice and dry. Although some hops along the outer edges of each layer were a bit less dry, I was satisfied. I divided them into 1oz batches and bagged them into freezer bags, pressing out as much air as I could and was left with an even 4 ounces total!</p>

<p>Where to go from here? The packages of hops are stored in my freezer while I plan out a recipe to use them in. I&rsquo;m planning on a SMaSH recipe. SMaSH stands for &ldquo;single malt and single hop&rdquo; so I can only use one type of malt and one type of hop. This will really showcase the Nugget hops and help me build the perfect recipe over the years as I continue to receive these hops from grandma!</p>

<p>Stay tuned for the recipe and brew notes!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DIY RIMS Tube, and Brewery Update]]></title>
    <link href="http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/08/29/diy-rims-tube/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-29T08:38:21-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/08/29/diy-rims-tube</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past few days, a bunch of new toys have steadily been arriving at my doorstep. But first, did I mention that <a href="/blog/2014/07/24/downsizing-sucks">my last post about the brewery</a> can go suck it? <!-- more -->Yeah, I wrote that post late at night while I was feeling a little overwhelmed and like my brewery would never happen. But I woke up the next morning with a renewed sense of purpose and just a generally uplifted can-do attitude. With the support of my amazing wife, I&rsquo;m going to make this brewery happen. The size of my pots, in the grand scheme of things, doesn&rsquo;t really change how the brewery would be built anyway. Sure, I&rsquo;ll still have to worry about where to put all my beer, but I&rsquo;ll deal with that when the time comes. Every other piece of the brewery would need to be built the same if the pots were 10G anyway, so I&rsquo;m sticking with the 20G setup.</p>

<h3>Brewery Update</h3>

<p>So the brewery build is back on track. Since the last post, I ripped up the bamboo laminate flooring and molding in the basement brew room, and rented and used a concrete floor sander from Home Depot to remove the existing paint on the floor. This weekend is Labor Day weekend and I have a lot of work to do. I need to finish cleaning up around the edges where the concrete sanding left behind a bunch of muck. After that I&rsquo;ll be putting down a coat of garage floor epoxy that I got custom mixed at Lowe&rsquo;s to match the color scheme I want for the brewery.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going for a super sleek/modern industrial look not unlike the <a href="http://www.theelectricbrewery.com/gallery">awesome basement brewery</a> designed by Kal, the creator of The Electric Brewery (the instructions I used to build my control panel). I&rsquo;m also pulling on a lot of inspiration from <a href="http://www.theelectricbrewery.com/testimonials">all the other</a> Electric Brewery setups out there. Even the names of the Valspar paint color swatches are pretty badass: &ldquo;High Speed Steel&rdquo; and &ldquo;Polished Silver&rdquo;. These colors are going to really make all the stainless steel equipment &ldquo;pop&rdquo;. Those toys I mentioned earlier included diamond plating outlet and switch covers, as well as some really nice looking brushed aluminum sheeting that is going to make a kickass backsplash on the wall behind the kettles. More on all that next week so stay tuned.</p>

<h3>Portable Brewery</h3>

<p>The basement brewery project is a huge undertaking and I really won&rsquo;t be able to use it until everything is done and in place. At this point, that&rsquo;s looking like it could still be a few months out. In the meantime, I&rsquo;ve been actively researching many other areas of homebrewing. I&rsquo;m playing around with a lot of stuff around automation with Raspberry Pi and Arduino. I also recently learned about PLCs (Programmable Logic Controllers) which is really interesting to me and I&rsquo;m sure you&rsquo;ll be seeing a post about all that soon. Anyway, back on track.</p>

<p>One of my goals that is running parrallel to my goal of the basement brewery is the idea of also having a very portable electric brewery that I could potentially take with me and brew at a friends house or at a local brew day. Obviously the 3 kettle 20G HERMS system isn&rsquo;t going to be leaving my basement without something short of a U-Haul. The goals of the portable brewery are:</p>

<ol>
<li>Uses 120v electricity to brew a 5G batch (5G in the keg)</li>
<li>Completely modular- can be used in more than one way</li>
<li>Supports 2 pumps with standard outlets (separate on/off switches)</li>
<li>Uses a single temp probe and PID for auto-tuning precise tempurature setpoints</li>
<li>Small footprint, portable</li>
<li>Keep it simple, stupid!</li>
</ol>


<p>So there are several pieces to this setup; the control panel (the brain!) and the separate modules. Right now the pico panel is in a non-working state&hellip; I have some debugging to do to diagnose what is going on with the solid-state relay which appears to not be working. For point #2, an example of another way to use this would be a sous-vide in the kitchen (this adds to the importance of a small footprint for the panel), which would involve a smaller heating element plugged into the panel, and a very tiny recirculation pump. Modular brewing options would be the RIMS tube or a brew-in-a-bag (BIAB) pot. Another whacky use would even be to apply this to the cold side of brewing. The PID is just as capable of turning a fermentation chamber on and off according to the low set point as it is for turning a heating element on for mashing/boiling! How cool is that?! Another modular piece of the equation is that the support for &ldquo;pumps&rdquo; is really just a couple of auxiliary outlets with switches, so you could plug a fan in there if that applies to the task at hand, or whatever you need. I&rsquo;m currently thinking through how to make one of the auxiliary outlets have 3 modes: on, off, and auto. The &ldquo;auto&rdquo; setting would fire along with the heating element, but still let you switch it off if needed. We&rsquo;ll see though, because it has to align with goal #6!</p>

<p>Here is the Pico Panel build and it being used as a sous-vide controller:</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="//imgur.com/a/BE1XY/embed"></iframe>


<h3>DIY RIMS Tube</h3>

<p>RIMS is a type of electric brewing system whereby the wort is heated directly during the mash as it is pumped over a heating element. This eliminates the need for a dedicated hot liquor tank, making it more portable and cheaper than a HERMS. In HERMS, you typically have 3 vessels, a mash tun with no heat applied directly, a hot liquor tank with heating element and a coil which the wort is pumped (circulated) through without contacting the hot water directly (the water is kept at mash temp by the element), and a boil kettle with heating element.</p>

<p>I found <a href="http://www.homebrewtalk.com/f51/rims-dummies-114997">an old thread on the HomeBrewTalk forums</a> for a cool design made out of regular stainless steel pipe fittings and opted to go that route rather than buying a pre-made shiny RIMS tube. I like the idea of being able to customize it however I want by unscrewing a fitting or two and maybe adding something in-line or making a change. The fittings are all 1.5" NPT 304 stainless. This thing is super beefy and I&rsquo;m a little worried that will make it difficult to heat on 120v, but we&rsquo;ll see. I sprung for a tri-clover to 1.5" NPT fitting so I could use a tri-clover heating element enclosure for easy cleaning. I really need to be able to easily dry the element after a brew because they are known to rust if left damp. The heating element I already had from the souse-vide doesn&rsquo;t want to fit nicely inside the RIMS tube, so I&rsquo;ll need to order another one, which is tricky because the product listings on Amazon for these things are notorious for being inaccurate. I really need an Ultra-Low Watt Density element to prevent scorching and to reduce the likelihood of an accidental dry-fire explosions (turning on the element without liquid on it to dissipate the heat) which are guaranteed on the high watt density elements.</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="//imgur.com/a/5mPuB/embed"></iframe>


<p>Well this blog post took way too long to finish (I started on 8-29 and minimized it until today, 9-5) so I&rsquo;m going to end it here, but stay tuned for more updates.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Downsizing Sucks]]></title>
    <link href="http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/07/24/downsizing-sucks/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-24T22:12:43-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/07/24/downsizing-sucks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s 10pm and, after debating the issue for quite a while now, I decided to take the first step in downsizing one of my hobbies. Downsizing a hobby really sucks, but sometimes it&rsquo;s for the best. In this case, the hobby is homebrewing. I&rsquo;ve been homebrewing for about 3 years, and the whole time has been on an upward trend as far as my obsession for it goes, but lately it has really taken a back seat. We recently bought our first house and in the move, and settling in, and enjoying all the new space and freedom (like beeing able to build a chicken coop), my half-baked 20 Gallon Electric Brewery project was put on hold. Well, I just posted my three, never been used, 20 gallon brew kettles for sale online&hellip;</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="http://imgur.com/a/S4t12/embed"></iframe>


<p><em>read on for my reasoning behind this terrible downsizing</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>After spending a year building an <a href="http://theelectricbrewery.com">Electric Brewery</a> control panel on my own, and just barely having seen it come to life before moving, I&rsquo;m already looking to downsize the system. Here are some of my reasons, which I&rsquo;m writing down partly because I&rsquo;m still trying to convince myself it is the right choice.</p>

<p>1) Our house is far from my workplace now. So what, right? Well one of my favorite parts about brewing was having friends and coworkers over and having a great brew day. One of the trade-offs of moving this far away for our dream house was that those friends likely won&rsquo;t be making the trip for brew day anymore. I don&rsquo;t blame them. It&rsquo;s over an hour by train and nearly as long in weekend traffic when driving.</p>

<p>2) Since I take that hour+ long train ride to work now, I won&rsquo;t be off-loading kegs of homebrew for the office keggerator any time soon. That leaves me with 3 kegs of beer after every brew day. What am I supposed to do with all that?</p>

<p>3) Trying to get through 15 gallons of beer after each brew session would require me to only brew once in a blue moon. My favorite part of brewing is the experimentation and exploration involved &ndash; <del>trying</del> creating new recipes. But sometimes, experiments fail. In fact many of my homebrew experiments have failed. Hell, I think I have 30 gallons of (probably) ruined/gross/meh homebrew in various states around my house (in the keggerator, in the breezeway sitting in carboys since the move, in kegs in the closet, in old bottles somewhere in the moving boxes) and I know I&rsquo;ve dumped that much down the drain early on. With the 20 gallon system, my minimum brew size would have been around 10 gallons, but more likely 15 gallons would be the average batch size. That is a lot of beer to mess up.. there is more on the line with the large system. I got cocky and made my system too big for my level of experience (although I planned to grow into it).</p>

<p>4) By selling <em>just one</em> of my kettles, I&rsquo;ll be able to get three new ones of a more reasonable size. Good news is, stainless steel doesn&rsquo;t really lose value in the homebrew world. I really like the MegaPot 1.2s, so I&rsquo;m planning on going with those again, but in the 8 gallon size. The remaining two pots I&rsquo;ll still sell, and hopefully with a piece of that I can afford a decent fermenter. Like a small conical or a couple of the new stainless steel &ldquo;bucket&rdquo; style fermenters which have a slight cone at the bottom. I really think not fermenting in stainless is the last major problem with my brewing (causing minor off flavors).</p>

<p>So there you have it. I&rsquo;ll be downsizing to an 8 gallon electric HERMs brewery. Yes, of course I&rsquo;ll still use my amazing control panel. Seriously, it took over a year to build.</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="http://imgur.com/a/8a12t/embed"></iframe>


<p>Cheers!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
