<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Chickens | Andrew Hammond]]></title>
  <link href="http://andrhamm.com/blog/categories/chickens/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://andrhamm.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-23T10:38:05-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://andrhamm.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Hammond]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chicken Coop Build Progress]]></title>
    <link href="http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/06/23/chicken-coop-build-progress/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-23T10:23:31-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://andrhamm.com/blog/2014/06/23/chicken-coop-build-progress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent another 25 hours or so on my chicken coop this weekend. I&rsquo;ll roll all this into a more detailed post at some point, but for now check out this album.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This weekend was mostly spent on the cabin part of the coop (as opposed to the larger, open &ldquo;run&rdquo;). This is where the chickens will roost at night. I decided to line the floor of the coop with linoleum flooring, to protect the wood from absorbing any of the nasty smells/fluids from the chicken waste. It should also make it much easier to clean out periodically.</p>

<p>The front of the coop has a window to let in some natural sunlight and allow for needed ventilation in the summer. I covered the window with hardware cloth (strong chicken wire) from the inside, but will add a sheet of clear plexy-glass before the fall/winter season for weather proofing.</p>

<p>The entire back side of the coop is a swinging door with a really beefy hinge (spring-loaded to prevent the door from remaining open) and latch. This door is essential for cleaning out the cabin and is the only way a person can get into the coop.</p>

<p>The siding is all tounge &amp; groove boards which makes for a very time-consuming build. I&rsquo;m not complaining though, my father-in-law Chuck had it left over from his house build and gave it to me for free! Similar boards at Lowe&rsquo;s run about $10 each. Each! I would have just left it at plywood if that was my only option, but I had so many of these boards left over that I figured this would be well worth the extra effort. I love how the siding looks, with its nice horizontal grooves, it really adds to the desired &ldquo;barn&rdquo; look. Of course the &ldquo;barn door red&rdquo; paint with white trim really paid off too!</p>

<iframe class="imgur-album" width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" src="http://imgur.com/a/jtQfY/embed"></iframe>


<p>Stay tuned for more updates on the coop.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
